A Guide to the Richmond Triangle Players Archives, 1992-2007
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library
Richmond Triangle Players Archives 1992-2007
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library
M 347
.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated by Michael Gooding in August 2005
Historical Information
In 1992, Marchcus Miller, Steve J. Earle and Mike Gooding produced a three night run of one act plays called Safe Sex based on Harvey Fierstein's trilogy. Fierstein gave special permission to add Forget Him which he had never let anyone else produce. The objective was to raise money for the AIDS crisis, which after 10 years of incubation in big cities, was then reaching serious proportions and looming large in the consciousness of Richmond. Richmond Triangle Players (RTP) were formed from this first production.
In the early years, RTP focused on AIDS related shows including As Is by William Hoffman, Elegies for Angels, Punks, & Raging Queens by Bill Russell and Steven Dietz's Lonely Planet. The intention was to make the company and its productions inclusive, bringing in new directors, and to offer opportunities to aspiring artists and playwrights. RTP efforts at consciousness raising have expanded to plays dealing with the Gay experience in many forms: breast cancer, diversity, aging and dying, and almost always dealing with relationships, especially as they affect those with alternative lifestyles.
Scope and Content
This collection is mostly composed of photographic and ephemeral material relating to the various productions that RTP has undertaken in the past 13 years. This includes advertisements, programs, and photos, and reviews. Most of the reviews were done by representatives from either the Richmond Times Dispatch or Style Weekly Magazine. Despite the lack of administrative records, the collection is rich in other ways. There is material related to a broad range of topics, from AIDS and gay/lesbian related issues to local (Richmond) personalities. Some of the first productions staged by RTP dealt with the AIDS crisis; shows like Ten Percent Revue and Lisbon Traviata attempted to shed light on this important aspect of gay experience. Other shows with a focus on AIDS include Elegies for Angels, Punks, and Raging Queens and Steve Moore's I Never Knew Oz Was in Color.
Homophobia is another theme that RTP address in their programming. The Richmond Triangle Players produced The Laramie Project in conjunction with another Richmond theatre group (Barksdale Theatre). The play focuses on the reactions of residents of the small town of Laramie, Wyoming to the brutal murder of gay college student, Matthew Shepard. Stop Kiss by Diana Son tells the story of a young woman who was attacked after she was seen kissing another woman.
Other prominent themes in RTPs productions include gay/lesbian relationships (The Most Fabulous Story Ever Told, The Judas Kiss, and Taken In) and growing up gay (Hysterical Blindness and I Never Knew Oz Was in Color). Despite a large number of productions devoted to gay/lesbian themes, RTP does not focus solely on these. My Left Breast is about one woman's struggle with breast cancer and The Last Session chronicles the experiences of a sex addict. Important locals within the collection include comedian Steve Moore and actress Marchy Sue Carroll.
Another important element of this collection is several Virginia gay/lesbian periodicals (Out in Virginia, Out and About, The Virginia Gayzette). These date from throughout the 1990s. Items of interest contained within them include gay reaction to Bill Clinton's first presidential campaign, the impact of AIDS on the gay community, as well as guides to gay establishments in the Richmond and Hampton Roads areas.
For other information about Richmond and AIDS see Fan Free Clinic Collection.
Arrangement
The contents of this collection are arranged chronologically according to the opening date of each production. The periodicals are arranged alphabetically following the production materials. There are 4 boxes; Box 1 contains production materials from Safe Sex and Lisbon Traviata in the first season to I Never Knew Oz Was in Color in the sixth season; Box 2 contains production materials from Stop Kiss in the seventh season to Eula Mae's Beauty, Bait, and Tackle in the tenth season; Box 3 contains production materials from My Left Breast to season 14; it also contains miscellaneous organizational files; Box 4 contains oversized publications. Posters relating to various productions are in Map Case 37.
Contents List
- Season 1 1993-1994 (Box 1)
  - Safe Sex, Harvey Fierstein, Clippings 1992 (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Safe Sex, Harvey Fierstein, Flyer 1992 (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Safe Sex, Harvey Fierstein, Poster 1992
  - Safe Sex, Harvey Fierstein, Programs 1992 (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Safe Sex, Harvey Fierstein, Tickets 1992 (Box-folder 1:4)
  - Lisbon Traviata, Terrence McNally, Clippings 13 October 1993 (Box-folder 1:5)
  - Lisbon Traviata, Terrence McNally, Correspondence 13 October 1993 (Box-folder 1:6)
  - Ten Percent review, Richard Maltby Jr./David Shire, Clippings November 1993 (Box-folder 1:7)
  - Ten Percent review, Richard Maltby Jr./David Shire, Photographs November 1993 (Box-folder 1:8)
  - Ten Percent review, Richard Maltby Jr./David Shire, Poster November 1993
  - Vampire Lesbians of Sodom and Sleeping Beauty or Coma, Charles Busch, Clippings December 1993 (Box-folder 1:9)
  - Vampire Lesbians of Sodom and Sleeping Beauty or Coma, Charles Busch, Flyer December 1993 (Box-folder 1:10)
  - Vampire Lesbians of Sodom and Sleeping Beauty or Coma, Charles Busch, Photographs December 1993 (Box-folder 1:11)
  - Vampire Lesbians of Sodom and Sleeping Beauty or Coma, Charles Busch, Poster December 1993
  - Vampire Lesbians of Sodom and Sleeping Beauty or Coma, Charles Busch, Program December 1993 (Box-folder 1:12)
  - Crazy Man, Jaqui Singleton, Clippings February 1994 (Box-folder 1:13)
  - Crazy Man, Jaqui Singleton, Photographs February 1994 (Box-folder 1:14)
  - Crazy Man, Jaqui Singleton, Poster February 1994
- Season 2 1994-1995 (Box 1)
  - Baltimore Waltz, Paula Vogel, Clippings September 1994 (Box-folder 1:15)
  - Baltimore Waltz, Paula Vogel, Photographs September 1994 (Box-folder 1:16)
  - Baltimore Waltz, Paula Vogel, Photographs September 1994
  - Elegies for Angels, Punks, and Raging Queens, Bill Russell, Clippings November 1994 (Box-folder 1:17)
  - Elegies for Angels, Punks, and Raging Queens, Bill Russell, Photographs November 1994 (Box-folder 1:18)
  - Elegies for Angels, Punks, and Raging Queens, Bill Russell, Posters November 1994
  - Kathy and Mo Show: Parallel Lives, Mo Gaffney/Kathy Najimy, Clippings February 1995 (Box-folder 1:19)
  - Kathy and Mo Show: Parallel Lives, Mo Gaffney/Kathy Najimy, Correspondence February 1995 (Box-folder 1:20)
  - Kathy and Mo Show: Parallel Lives, Mo Gaffney/Kathy Najimy, Fliers and Programs February 1995 (Box-folder 1:21)
  - Kathy and Mo Show: Parallel Lives, Mo Gaffney/Kathy Najimy, Photographs February 1995 (Box-folder 1:22)
  - Kathy and Mo Show: Parallel Lives, Mo Gaffney/Kathy Najimy, Receipts February 1995 (Box-folder 1:23)
  - Kathy and Mo Show: Parallel Lives, Mo Gaffney/Kathy Najimy, Stage Directions February 1995 (Box-folder 1:24)
  - Boys in the Band, Matt Crowley, Clippings March 1995 (Box-folder 1:25)
  - Boys in the Band, Matt Crowley, Program March 1995 (Box-folder 1:26)
- Season 3 1995-1996 (Box 1)
  - Get Used to It!, Tom Wilson Weinberg, Clippings October 1995 (Box-folder 1:27)
  - Get Used to It!, Tom Wilson Weinberg, Program and Ticket October 1995 (Box-folder 1:28)
  - Her Aching Heart, Bryany Lavery, Photographs January 1996 (Box-folder 1:29)
  - Finishing it Off!, Mary Jane Walsh, Clippings March 1996 (Box-folder 1:30)
- Season 4 1996-1997 (Box 1)
  - Fairy Tales, Eric Lane Barnes, Bills and Receipts March 1997 (Box-folder 1:32)
  - Fairy Tales, Eric Lane Barnes, Clippings March 1997 (Box-folder 1:33)
  - Fairy Tales, Eric Lane Barnes, Correspondence March 1997 (Box-folder 1:34)
  - Fairy Tales, Eric Lane Barnes, Photographs March 1997 (Box-folder 1:34)
  - Christina Darling, Daniel Ruth, Flyer and Program April 1997 (Box-folder 1:35)
  - Christina Darling, Daniel Ruth, Photographs April 1997 (Box-folder 1:36)
  - Christina Darling, Daniel Ruth, Script April 1997 (Box-folder 1:37)
  - White Noise, Daniel Ruth, Clippings July 1996 (Box-folder 1:38)
  - White Noise, Daniel Ruth, Program July 1996 (Box-folder 1:39)
  - Deranged Durang: An Evening of Dementia, Christopher Durang, Program Undated (Box-folder 1:40)